You who listen and watch, learn that killing
a Sloughi is as serious as killing 7 men.
It has been said by the poet
that the Sloughi is not a dog.
Among all creatures, the sloughi, by its grace and nobility, gladdens the soul of its master and fills him with pride.
For 5000 years, it has inspired the stories of men.
Here is a story among stories for you.
Hassen is a hunter. And his sloughi is his
only weapon. Hassen doesn't own a sloughi.
But both are possessed by hunting fever.
Six years ago, Hassen was a simple
shepherd with a few sheep.
Then one day, an old hunter gave him his
sloughi, but he never wanted to say where it came from.
Hassen named her Janah.
Janah means bird's wing.
Because of all the sloughis, Janah is the fastest.
But one morning fate caught up with Janah,
leading him to a place he should never have gone.
On the land of the caïd. Lord and master of the place.
Beside the princess of the Sloughis, her servant Yasmina.
At the foot of the caïd's sloughia tree, a light of beauty.
But you don't disturb the boss's Sloughia.
And we don't speak to the maid Yasmina.
If this meeting had not taken place, Janah's story would have been very different.
As for Hassen the hunter, he was far from guessing what was going to happen.
The Sloughia lives in the Caïd's palace.
He named her Ziya.
Ziya means light.
She is the velvet of his soul.
Everyone knows that the kingpin indulges his every whim.
For the past year, Ziya, the pearl of his eyes,
has been old enough to bear children.
For a year now, the crime boss has been looking for a suitor worthy of his princess.
He wants the most beautiful sloughi in the whole province for her.
He entrusted the moqadem, his hunting leader,
with this important mission.
Every day, the moqadem presents him with males.
But none of them are worthy of Ziya.
If this continues, there could soon be
another Moqadem in place of the Moqadem.
To please his boss and regain his favor,
the Moqadem came up with an idea.
From the moqadem's mouth, everyone must learn that
the caïd is looking for a male worthy of his sloughia.
All suitors must present themselves at the palace.
A major hunt will take place to select the best one.
As a reward, a horse. A horse from the Palace stables.
But above all, let's not see any bastards there.
That day, Hassen understood that Janah's destiny was about to be fulfilled.
Of all the Sloughis, Janah possesses the finest qualities.
Its jaw is powerful, its shoulders are muscular, its chest is deep, its ears are set perfectly high.
Hassen always knew that his sloughi
was of the highest nobility.
May it be Janah who chooses you to become a prince.
As soon as the boss sees you, he'll know.
They came from all the valleys.
For the horse, of course, but above all
for the promise of a princely wedding.
Everyone knows their sloughi is the best.
But of all of them, only one will be elected.
The moqadem's eye sees everything. And his finger points to
those who are authorized to appear before the caïd.
Janah's story could have ended here. Her worth recognized, definitively.
But unfortunately for her, Yasmina, the Sloughia's servant, was also the Moqadem's daughter.
The Moqadem is a more jealous father than all fathers.
No one has the right to speak to his daughter.
And certainly not a poor shepherd like Hassen.
So the moqadem attacked Janah.
And he found all the faults in the world.
Thus, Janah could not show herself to the eyes of the caïd and his betrothed.
And Hassen's pride was wounded to the point of outrage.
Cursed be the moqadem.
As for Janah's love affair, the sloughi with the sloughia,
Hassen was sure they would never see each other again.
But the twists of fate are infinitely mysterious.
It was written that the servant Yasmina held
in her hands the destiny of Janah's love.
The Moqadem watches over the lands of the caïd
like a father watches over his daughter.
And that day, he called Hassen every name under the sun.
Nothing can stop a dispute between two hunters. Nothing.
Except to learn that a large hare has been seen in the area.
The young shepherd boy spoke of a hare the size of a gazelle.
This is the opportunity chosen by the master to
test the abilities of the contenders.
The hare sleeps during the day.
It's so low-lying that you could step on it without realizing it.
Smells, finding smells.
One lead.
Follow your instincts.
And Janah's nose.
Hassen never hunts in driven hunts. He is
like the hare. He doesn't like noise.
The hare is cunning. It moves by hopping.
And whoever follows its scent suddenly loses it.
So, you have to guess its route.
If only the kingpin had been able to see Janah.
If only the sloughia could tell the caïd.
On that day, Janah defied her destiny.
And the chieftain, who had never seen her before, noticed
the beauty of this sloughi that had been hidden from him.
Through Yasmina, he learned Janah's name.
He could learn nothing from Hassen's mouth.
So he wanted to see with his own eyes.
There are few sloughis that know how to capture a hare without killing it.
It's a female, and enormous because she
will soon have babies.
O you who escaped the pack of the caïd,
Let it be written that you will live long and that your children, when they are born, will learn of your cunning.
The caïd had seen Janah, but he did not know
the offense committed by his moqadem.
Everyone dreams of owning a thoroughbred horse. But a horse,
however beautiful, will not redeem Janah's honor.
The offense committed against Janah will separate him from Ziya forever.
Learn, Hassen, that you are not worth our attention.
A man's honor is worthless if he cannot see the sorrow of his faithful Sloughi.
There is no offense that cannot be forgiven.
Thus ended the story of Janah and the sloughia.
Instead of the horse, Hassen asked the chief to
take the young Sloughi of his choice,
And the chief granted his request. For the chief is great and just.
O you who listen, you will remember that this one
is not a stranger among strangers.
His name is Janah's son.
He will be a prince among princes.
So be it.